we need to write a loop
that prints numbers one through five and
whether the number is
even or odd and we've been given some
example output to look at
so we're going to use the code we've
been given as usual there
is more than one way to solve this
problem
looking at the code we've been given we
have a local variable count
initialized on line one referencing the
integer one
and then on lines three through five we
have a loop
now as this code has been given to us
this loop
is an infinite loop and we can
actually see that in action by
[Music]
printing count to the screen and running
our code
as you can see our loop is just running
over and over
and our count variable is incrementing
each time
remember to break out of an infinite
loop and exit the program we can hit
control
c on our keyboard
so let's look back at our code
we know we need to provide a break
condition here
and we want to count up until our number
is
5.
so let's insert break and add the
condition
[Music]
if count is equal to five
and let's just try to run our code again
now
okay and you can see we have printed out
numbers
one two three four and five and that's
exactly what we wanted to do
[Music]
so we're incrementing our account
variable and
breaking out of the loop appropriately
now what we need to do
is print out that the number is even
or the number is odd we can think about
this
in terms of an if statement
if the remainder of count divided by 2
is equal to 0
then count is an even number
in that case we want to output count is
even to the screen
now we can achieve this with either
string concatenation
or string interpolation in this case
let's use string interpolation
and we'll just format our output
according to the
example output that we were given
now if count is not even then we know
it's odd those are the only two
possibilities
[Music]
so if the first branch of our if
statement doesn't execute then we know
we're dealing with an odd number
and we want to output that the number is
odd
so let's run our code as it is now and
see what our output looks like
[Music]
okay and this is the expected behavior
so everything is looking correct
let's look back at our code and consider
some changes that we could make
there is a ruby integer method even
that we could use here on line four and
that will return a boolean as well
so it's fine to use this built-in ruby
method
if the number is even it will return the
boolean true
and the first branch of this if
statement will execute
but you'll see the same behavior
with this logic that we wrote out
earlier as well
a comparison like this will also return
a boolean
so if you didn't know the even method
that would be just fine it's okay to
write out your own logic
so just to demonstrate that this code
would work the same
using the even method we can run our
code one more time
and we'll see that the output is the
same
another option here would be to use a
ternary operator
[Music]
and this can make our code look a little
bit more concise
but perhaps a little bit less readable
[Music]
again calling the even method on count
will return a boolean
and if that boolean is true then ruby
will execute
the code on the left side of the colon
[Music]
if it returns false ruby will execute
the code on the right side of the colon
so let me just remove this code here i
forgot my exclamation point
but you can see that the output is the
same here so
this is just another example of there
being many different ways to
solve a problem and achieve the same
result
now this code may not seem as intuitive
or as
readable to you as the if statement
and that's okay it's okay to use longer
code that is more readable
now one thing to be aware of if you were
to solve this problem a little bit
differently
is to always be aware of where you're
incrementing
your counter and where you're placing
your break statement
so if we had initialized count to zero
we would want to increment our count
variable
up here prior to evaluating whether the
number is even or odd
if we only want to output numbers 1
through 5.
if we incremented the count variable
prior to checking its value
to determine whether to break out of the
loop then we may need to change the
comparison used as a condition
of our break statement so let's just do
a quick demonstration of that
[Music]
if we increment count prior to checking
its value
to break out of the loop then you can
see that we actually
only print numbers one through four
and that's not the correct output
what we would have to do is change our
comparison on line 11
to check whether count is greater than 5
so that the loop will still execute once
more
when count is equal to 5.
as you can see now the code is working
as we expected again
so it's just something to always be
conscious of
always be aware of
where are your incrementing count
variables and exactly how
you are checking their value as a
condition of your break